Hi, everyone. I'm Dr.
Ventimiglia, and today
we are preparing for the
beginning of osteopathy
in the cranial field.
We're going to do a
couple of labs in this
regard, and today's pre
-lab lecture is really
just to get you prepared
for what we're going
to do in lab this week.
um also it may feel a little
bit overwhelming because
we're reviewing a bunch
of things in anatomy
and physiology and i'm
going to go rather quickly
through this because it's
just a pre lab lecture but
i'd really like you to
take the time to um look
through each slide and
review that anatomy for
yourself. The objectives
for our lab are going to be
with regard to the cranial
landmarks, which are
important, not just in
identifying where they are, but
also for palpation, which
we're going to be doing
when we're sensing using
the different contacts,
as well as we'll be describing
or I will be reviewing
the normal physiologic
motion, which is occurring
at the sphenobasilar
junction and the axis of
motion with regard to the
sphenoid and the occiput.
And at the end of this
whole little section, at the
end of my lab, I do have a
few sensing exercises that
can be helpful because
there's a couple of different
things that are really
important in understanding
how to sense what it is that
we're going to be doing.
So let's jump in.
First of all, this is a
very significant list of
landmarks. And what I'd
like you to do with this,
besides running through the
pictures that I have following,
is to please please go
through palpating as
much of those landmarks on
the list as possible with
your own head and a friend
or family member's head
would be ideal because we
really want you to be able
to identify them when we
go through this in lab.
We want it to be like, this
is the third time you've
done it. So now you really
are getting it quickly.
The five phenomena of
the primary respiratory
mechanism as a review,
I really hope you've
all watched the lecture
with regard to this
lab. If not, please stop
now and go watch it,
is five parts to the primary
respiratory mechanism.
First is the inherent motility
of the brain and spinal
cord. So the central nervous
system itself has an inherent
motion, or we call it
motility. The fluctuation of
the cerebral spinal fluid
and the potency of the tide.
Three is the mobility of
the dural membranes. We call
that the reciprocal tension
membrane, meaning that
it's attaching in multiple
places to multiple bones
and it's reciprocating motion,
right? As it's following
what's happening with those
bones and that motility
of the brain and spinal
cord. The mobility of
those cranial bones, the
vault bones, they develop in
membrane as a newborn so
that they can fold up to
come through the birth
canal. And the cranial base
itself is developing in
cartilage. And so the vault is
really following what's
happening at the base. Okay.
And lastly, the involuntary
mobility of the sacrum
between the ilia. So we know
that the dura is attaching
at the level of S2, and
that the sacrum is also
moving in this primary
respiratory motion because of
its attachment to that
reciprocal tension membrane.
So just to recap, the motility
of the central nervous
system is a coiling and
uncoiling, And it begins
early on as the developmental
motion when the sperm
and the egg meet. The
notochord is moving in this
primary respiratory
motion, and it's moving
synchronously with these phases
of the primary respiratory
motion. The dura is
surrounding that. The cerebral
spinal fluid is in between
and also inside the
central nervous system in
the space of the ventricles,
and the cranial bones
are housing this system.
so with regard to the
mobility of the dura we are
going to know that they
act as check ligaments and
therefore they're guiding
and limiting the movement
of the cranial bones
this motion is much like
an arc and of a sickle
and so it's operating from
a fulcrum which is found
along the straight sinus.
Just a few other
pictures of that
to remind you of this anatomy.
So please look over those
pictures and have
a sense of that.
We say in osteopathy,
anatomy, anatomy, anatomy. And
so we're just sort of
reviewing all of this quickly
so that when we come to
lab and we put our hands
on to start sensing, we
have these clear pictures in
our mind of what it is
that we're trying to sense.
This is the sphenobasilar
synchondrosis, right?
There is your pituitary
gland, and this is a great
review of a lot of the
important cranial nerves
and their exit because
they are piercing through
the dura in order to perform
their function or get
to where they're going,
but strains in the dura,
strains in the cranial bone
will or potentially can
affect how these nerves are
performing and functioning.
Also, what is housed in the
reciprocal tension membrane
is your venous sinus
drainage. So we know that the
arteries are coming up
through the carotid and the
vertebral artery. And then
there is exchange through
the venous system, which is
going to be returning the
blood significantly back
to the heart. And so those
venous sinuses, which is
an interesting word, and I
think some students sometimes
don't fully understand
what that means, but sinus
technically means space.
And so the dura folds themselves
come together and create
spaces which are where
the venous blood is going
to be draining through. And
it is a system that we see
as part of the Falk's
cerebrum coming down toward
the back of the head in by
the confluence of sinuses,
and then we have the,
I'm sorry, the tentorium
cerebelli, and we have
the straight sinus,
as well as the then
sigmoid sinus going down
toward, you can see here
in this picture, going down
toward the jugular
foramen and then becoming
the jugular vein and
returning back to the heart.
What we'll be looking at
with the sutures is their
motion. So the cranial bones
come together. They are
plates that are developing
in utero. And as the child
is growing, they will begin
to develop certain sorts
of accommodations in how
they're coming together or
sutures. A best example of
this is the serrate suture,
which is an interlocking
spicules, which allow for
motion. And we see this
most significantly in the
sagittal suture, which is
between the parietal bones.
And that is where is of a
greatest motion. Underneath
that is right the sagittal
dural sinus, which is an
interesting thought is that
why we have such motion in an
area where veins themselves
are not able to pump blood
back or sinuses. So we
don't want pooling of blood.
That motion at that
serrated suture helps
to support motion of
blood flow back through
the venous sinus system and
into the jugular foramen.
Another example of a suture
is a squamous suture.
And so I'd really like
for you to get a sense of
what these feel like just
by palpating them. get a
sense of what does a
serrated suture feel like
following the sagittal suture
on your own two parietal
bones. And then if you
find your parietal bones,
you can come down and
you'll get a feeling of what
squamous suture feels
like, a sort of overlapping
of the parietal and
the temporal bone.
And that suture is also
having interdigitation
and it has more of
a gliding motion.
So the movement of the
primary respiratory mechanism
is an alternating change
in shape of the cranium.
And we call two different
phases, the inhalation
phase and the exhalation
phase. And during each of these
phases, different things
are occurring. so in in
the system of all of those
five parts so during the
inhalation phase the cranium
is widening transversely
in this direction everything
that's paired is moving
into external rotation
but in ap diameter it is
getting narrow and then
that would be called flexion
and then in exhalation,
now the AP diameter becomes
longer and the paired parts
go into internal rotation,
and that is extension or
exhalation phase. And so
we will be spending some
time in lab working to get
a sense of this normal
physiologic motion that is
occurring in our body all
the time. And it starts
again at conception and
continues on throughout life.
So all the midline
bones rotate through a,
this is of the cranial
base. All the midline
bones of the cranial base
rotate through transverse
axes and they move in
a gear like motion.
So again, transverse axes,
if I have a pen, is going
to be in this direction.
Let's see, my pen doesn't
show. Okay, it's going
to be, here's my finger.
Transverse action axis is
going to be rotating in a
flexion and extension motion,
transverse axis, right?
If we have an AP
axis, then we are
moving inside bending.
and if we have a
vertical axis, that
becomes rotation.
So again, we've learned
all of this last year
and now we're just
applying it to the cranial
bones. Their axes are all
a little bit different,
but the midline bones
all have transverse axes.
The other bones have
very complicated axes.
We're not talking about
them right here, but
certainly we want you to
understand the midline
motion and that is
going to be moving in
opposite directions in
gear-like fashion, okay?
So the mobility of
the cranial bones
are moving in flexion
and extension,
and the paired bones are
moving in external and
internal rotation, and
the bones of the sacrum,
okay, here's just a quick
review of inhalation and
exhalation, the bones of
the sacrum are going to be
following. So the sacrum is
in five pieces at birth and
doesn't fully fuse until
the age of 25, but the dura
is attaching anteriorly
at the level of S2. And so
the sacral base or the top
of the sacrum, is going to
be moving in the flexion or
inhalation phase superiorly
and posteriorly. And then
in the exhalation phase,
it's going to be moving
inferiorly and anteriorly.
Okay.
So with beginning sensing,
we are going to be
talking about ergonomics,
just changing gears a little
bit, that was your
anatomy, anatomy, anatomy.
And now we're going to
be getting ready to come
to the tables and getting
a sense of these things.
So this is a little
bit of a jump for a lot
of you because we were
doing a lot when we were
assessing things such as
the transverse processes
of the spine. We were
putting a lot of pressure
on muscle. We were
getting a sense of muscle.
Here, we're going to be
switching gears a little bit
and we're still observing,
but now we're going to
be using the proprioceptors
of our hands. Our hands
and actually the soles
of our feet are heavily
innervated with proprioceptors,
which feel for fine
motion. And so it is important
when trying to feel for
this, that we are going
to be relaxed and paying
attention to our own posture
and our own breathing.
So we want to be comfortable
and we may need to
adjust ourself, but we also
need to keep continually
checking in with ourself
because as we check in
with ourself and we know
that we're comfortable
and relaxed, that will
translate to what is happening
with our hands. If we're
tense and we're squeezing
really hard on our
patient's head, our patients
are going to feel that,
our partners are going
to feel that, and they
might feel uncomfortable.
Whereas we want to be
really chill and relaxed and
supported so that we can
just sort of sense. Sensing
means receiving or afferently
receiving information as
opposed to efferently coming
in and doing something.
So we don't have to do
anything in this lab so far
today. We will at the end
of the lab. But in the
beginning parts of the lab,
we're going to be coming
in with an open mind for
sensing. And this may be
something that some of you
have already done if you've
already paid attention to
your own breathing, your
own diaphragm motion with
regard to taking meditation
or yoga classes or
something, Qigong. However,
now we're going to be
using some of those skills
for ourself, but we'll be
dividing our attention so
we can observe ourself
and what we're palpating.
Different contacts
that we're going to be
using, I'm just going to
quickly run through the
name of each of them.
The vault contact is
for palpating the vault,
which are the vault
bones, frontal, greater
wing of the sphenoid,
parietal, the squamous
portion of the temporal,
and the squamous portion
of the occiput. So we
will be getting a sense
of how the vault is
moving and let's remember
that the vault is actually
just moving in accommodation
for what's happening
at the base where
the sphenoid and the
occiput come together, the
sphenobasilar junction.
The frontal occipital contact
is another great contact.
And we use different
contacts in order for sensing
and for treating because
sometimes it gives us a different
view of what's going on
with the anatomy. I happen
to like all of these contacts
and use them all, but
the frontal occipital contact
happens to be exceptionally
good for palpating the
dura and getting a sense of
those attachments of the
dura and then how that feels.
The Becker hold is another
one wonderful hold in which
we get a sense of the
posterior cranial fossa. And
in this case, you can see
the thumbs are reaching up
toward the greater wing of
the sphenoid. I also use
this contact when I'm treating
children because their
heads are smaller and it
helps to give me a sense of
the cranial base, a little
bit of what's happening with
the vault. And then my
fingertips are reaching down
toward the neck so I can get
a sense of what's happening
also at the cervical
cranial junction or the OA.
There's a modified version
or variation of this in
which we now take the thumbs
and put them behind the
ears. And remember, in all
of these contacts, it is most
important that we are
relaxed and we're coming with
an idea of sensing and
feeling something, feeling
life in motion, as opposed
to squeezing something or
trying to feel something.
So we're going to get there.
Okay. This is the cranial
contact unilateral
temporal hold.
Actually, I think we
are not doing this
at this time. we're
going to save this for
a different lecture.
But let's talk about the
technique, okay? So we're
going to be doing the
OA decompression, which
is a wonderful technique.
It is something that I
use every time on every
patient, sometimes twice.
Dr. Ann Wales, who was a
student of Dr. Sutherland's,
would say, treat the
OA in the beginning
and treat the OA at the
end of every treatment.
And so we'll be going
over this in lab, but know
that there are other
alternatives to treating it as
well. And in this case,
this is going to be in the
atlas. And this can be an
important way of treating
the OA in the pediatric
population because their
cranial bones are not as
connected like ours through
the sutures. There's still
sort of plates floating
around and therefore we
want to make sure that
we're using techniques
that are being used to be
safe for different developmental
stages of the body.
Three exercises to do
before class. So we're
going to be introducing
some of these in
class and you're welcome
to give them a try.
I think it's worth
practicing here, even for
your own relaxation
and self-introspection.
Exercise one is in sensing
your own inherent motion.
That would be exercise two is
sensing the hole in a patient.
So starting from the feet,
getting a sense of the
hole and, or starting from
the head. Notice this is at
home, do it yourself. so
this is something you can
do if you have a bed or a
couch and a chair and I'd
also like to point out and
I want to point out that
I use a pillow under my
arms so that I have a place
for relaxing and that my
feet are flat on the floor
so that I'm very comfortable
as I'm trying to sense
and another wonderful place
for feeling and sensing
motion is in anything else
that's alive So you're
welcome to get a sense of
a tree, your animals, pets.
Okay.
I think that's about it.
Stop sharing.
There we go. And so I'm
sure you're going to all
have a lot of questions,
but again, please review
the anatomy, not just
by looking at the
pictures, which is very
important, but also at home.
If you can palpate those
landmarks on yourself,
it's going to really give
you a step up for when
we get to lab. Okay.
I'll see you guys in lab.